Guide to the William Conklin Cusick Papers 1906-1924
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
William Conklin Cusick Papers
1906-1924
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
Cage 316
Cusick, William C. (William Conklin), 1842-1922
0.5 Linear feet of shelf space 1 Box 24 Items
Cusick’s extant papers consist primarily of his field books, which doubled as the catalog for the second herbarium, and the draft list of the floral surveys he conducted about 1910.
William C. Cusick was born in Illinois in 1842 and emigrated to Oregon while a youth. He had a modest "collegiate" education and worked as a teacher for a time. Most of his adult life he spent as a rancher in the area of the Wallowa Mountains. He began botanical collecting and distribution sometime in the 1870s, encouraged by Harvard’s Asa Gray. Most of his plants came from the area of the Wallowa and Blue Mountains and were arranged in two successive herbariums, one of which he transferred to the University of Oregon, while the second went to Washington State University.
Encouraged by C. V. Piper, Cusick’s second herbarium project included extensive and exhaustive botanical surveys of the area in the two mountain ranges. Unlike his earlier efforts, this second phase did not include large distributions of plants. Cusick died in 1922.
William C. Cusick’s extant papers consist primarily of his field books, which doubled as the catalog for the second herbarium, and the draft list of the floral surveys he conducted, circa 1900-1910. A few surviving items of correspondence with C. V. Piper, and a biographical sketch of Cusick by W. W. Eggleston are also included.
The Cusick papers are arranged to content, with the meager extant correspondence segregated. The field books follow Cusick’s numbering system.
This collection is open and available for research use.
The papers of William C. Cusick, 1842-1922, of Union County, Oregon, were acquired by the Washington State University Herbarium about 1921, along with Cusick’s Second Herbarium
The materials in this collection of botanical documents were transferred to the Washington State University Library in 1975 from the university’s Ownbey Herbarium.
Cusick’s life and botanical experiences are discussed in Irwin F. Lange, Pioneer Botanists of the Pacific Northwest, Oregon Historical Quarterly, 57 (1956) 115-118 and Harold St. John, William Conklin Cusick, Rhodora, 25 (1923) 101-105.
Northwest Botanical Manuscripts: an Indexed Register of the Papers, 1867-1957, of Wilhelm Nikolaus Suksdorf, William Conklin Cusick, Charles Vancouver Piper, Rolla Kent Beattie, and Harold St. John in the Washington State University Library. Washington State University; 1976.
Northwest Botanical Manuscripts: an Indexed Register of the Papers, 1867-1957, of Wilhelm Nikolaus Suksdorf, William Conklin Cusick, Charles Vancouver Piper, Rolla Kent Beattie, and Harold St. John in the Washington State University Library. Washington State University; 1976.
Washington State University Botanical Papers, 1881-1973 (Cage 53)
Xerpha Mae Gaines Papers, 1948-1970 (Cage 122)
Wilhelm Nikolaus Suksdorf Papers, 1867-1935 (Cage 315)
Charles Vancouver Piper Papers, 1888-1926 (Cage 317)
Rolla Kent Beattie Papers, 1899-1956 (Cage 318)
Harold St. John Papers, 1912-1957 (Cage 319)
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Cusick, William C. (William Conklin), 1842-1922 -- Archives.; Piper, Charles V. (Charles Vancouver), 1867-1926.; Eggleston, W. W. (Willard Webster), 1863-1935.
Botanists -- United States -- Correspondence.; Botany -- Research -- Oregon.
Science; Colleges and Universities; Washington (State)
- Correspondence, letters from C. V. Piper, 1914-1921; 3 items. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Biographical Sketch of Cusick by Willard W. Eggleston, 1924; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- A Catalogue of Grasses of Eastern Oregon, 1908; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- A List, From Memory, of the Plants to be Seen Near at Hand in Crossing the Canyon of the Immaha Near its Source, 1911; 3 items. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- An Annotated List of the Flowering Plants and Ferns of Northeastern Oregon: Wallawa, Union, Baker and Umatilla Counties, 1909; 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Distribution of Characteristic Alpine and Hudsonian Plants of the Wallowa Mountains, undated; 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Distribution of Characteristic Alpine and Hudsonian Plants of the Wallowa Mountains, undated; 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Field Books/Catalogs 1906-1916
  - Specimen Number 2739-2783 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Specimen Number 3060-3145 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Specimen Number 3150-3339 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Specimen Number 3340-3420 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Specimen Number 1 (3509)-51 (3560) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Specimen Number 3422-3709 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Specimen Number 3710-4038 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Specimen Number 4039-4241 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Specimen Number 4242-4435 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Specimen Number 4436-4522 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Specimen Number 4546-4783 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Specimen Number 4604-4883 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Specimen Number 4884-4935 (Box 1, Folder 19)